Finding Aid for Stone-McCalmont Family Papers, 1832-1930
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Stone-McCalmont Family Papers 1832-1930
Stone Family
2 linear feet
85493 Aa 2
Macomb County and Kalamazoo, Michigan, family. Papers of Addison Ray Stone, graduate of the University of Michigan Medical School, later assistant surgeon in the 5th Michigan Cavalry during the Civil War, including medical school theses and notes and letters to his wife during the war; papers of William A. Stone, physician concerned with mental illness, assistant superintendent of the Michigan State Hospital for the Insane at Kalamazoo; papers of Dr. Harriette Stone, assistant physician at the State Hospital, containing letters from her father, Samuel P. McCalmont, Republican legislator from Pennsylvania, later founder of that state's Prohibition Party; papers of William A. Stone, Jr., and other members of Stone, McCalmont, Osborn, and Keeler families; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Isabel R. Stone (donor no. 6200 ) and came to the library in 1978.
The collection is open to research.
Members of the Stone family of Macomb County and Kalamazoo, Michigan, the McCalmont family of Pennsylvania, and the Osborn and Keeler family of New York state included both physicians and civic and political figures.
Dr. A. R. (Addison Ray) Stone was an 1854 graduate of the University of Michigan Medical School and served one year during 1862-1863 as assistant surgeon of the 5th Regiment Michigan Cavalry.
Dr. W. A. (William Addison) Stone was an 1885 graduate of the University of Michigan Medical School and a lecturer there in 1905-1906. He became a specialist in nervous and mental diseases and was for 19 years assistant superintendent of the Michigan State Hospital for the Insane at Kalamazoo, where he became known as an innovator of new methods in the institutional care of the insane.
Born at Franklin, Pennsylvania, Dr. Harriette Osborn McCalmont Stone graduated in 1893 from the Women's Medical College of Pennsylvania at Philadelphia and came to Kalamazoo, Michigan in 1897 to serve as assistant physician at the Michigan State Hospital for the Insane. In 1898 she married Dr. William Addison Stone, then assistant superintendent of that same institution. She was active in several professional and social organizations though most of her papers pre-date those associations.
Samuel Plumer McCalmont was a prominent Pennsylvania lawyer and businessman, onetime state legislator, leader in the formation of the Republican Party and delegate to the first Republican National Convention. He broke with the party over the temperance issue, becoming in 1874 a founder of the Prohibition Party in Pennsylvania, and publisher of perhaps the country's first Prohibition Party newspaper.
The Stone-McCalmont family papers date from about 1832-1930 and contain materials relating to different family members. The collection has been arranged by name of family.
Subjects:
Hospitals--Michigan.; Kalamazoo (Mich.); Keeler family.; McCalmont family.; Macomb County (Mich.); Medicine--Michigan.; Michigan Asylum for the Insane at Kalamazoo.; Osborn family.; Physicians--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Prohibition--Pennsylvania.; Prohibition Party (Pa.); United States. Army. Michigan Cavalry Regiment, 5th (1862-1865); United States--Politics and government--1865-1900.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Medicine and Surgery.; Women physicians--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Almont (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Almont.; McCalmont family.; Physicians--Michigan--Almont.; Stone, Addison Ray, 1828-1888.; Stone, William A. (William Addison), 1862-1924.
Contributors:
McCalmont, Samuel P. (Samuel Plumer), 1823-1904.; Stone, Addison Ray, 1828-1888.; Stone, Harriette, 1867-; Stone, William A. (William Addison), 1862-1924.; Stone, William A. (William Addison), 1902-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Woodcuts.
- Dr. Addison Ray Stone (1828-1888)
  The papers of Dr. Addison Ray Stone include some of his medical school notes and theses on such topics as the medicinal uses of opium and the symptoms, diagnosis and treatment of measles. Also included are his letters to his wife Ellen "Nellie" Gertrude Jenness Stone describing daily life and the battle activities of his regiment during the Civil War. His wife's papers contain letters written to her husband during his Civil War service.
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - December 1851-January 1853 August-December 1862 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1863 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1863 February 1871-February 1872 January 1888 (Box 1)
  - Medical School notes (Box 1)
  - Medical School Theses (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Ellen "Nellie" Gertrude Jenness Stone (d. 1900)
  (wife of Dr. A.R. Stone)
  - Correspondence August 1862, July-August 1863 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Nellie Stebbins Stone (1873-1910)
  (a niece of Dr. A.R. and Mrs. Nellie G. Stone)
  - Biographical and Autograph books 1881-1888, 1884 (Box 1)
- Dr. William Addison Stone (1862-1924)
  (nephew of Dr. A.R. Stone)
  The papers of Dr. William Addison Stone, nephew of Dr. A.R. Stone, includes biographical materials and various writings. Some of his later correspondence is found in the papers of his son, William Addison Stone, Jr.
  - Biographical material and correspondence (Box 1)
  - Writings and miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Resolutions adopted on the occasion of his retirement from the Michigan Asylum, Kalamazoo 1909 (Box 1)
- William Addison Stone, Jr. (b. 1902)
  (son of Dr. W.A. Stone)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1910-1916 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1917 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1917 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1918 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1918 (Box 1)
    - 1919 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1920 (Box 1)
    - 1926, 1928, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Writings and miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Samuel Plumer McCalmont (1823-1904)
  Dr. Harriette Stone's father, Samuel Plumer McCalmont was an active social reformer and his letters to his daughter are especially informative on economic and political developments of the time.
  - Correspondence 1896-1902 (Box 1)
  - Papers (Box 1)
- Harriet Osborn McCalmont
  (wife of Samuel P. McCalmont)
  The papers of Dr. Harriette Osborn McCalmont Stone comprise the bulk of the collection and consist of correspondence from her immediate family dating 1878-1898, the years of her education and early medical practice.
  - Correspondence, undated 1885, 1888, 1898-1904 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous McCalmont and Stone Family Members
  - Correspondence 1869-1918 (Box 1)
- Cynthia Ann Keeler
  (wife of J[osiah] R. Keeler)
  - Correspondence-1832? 1835, 1838, 1846, 1851-1852 (Box 1)
- David O[sborn?] Keeler
  (son of J.R. and C.A. Keeler)
  - Correspondence September-December 1852 (Box 1)
  - Poetry and compositions (Box 1)
- William Henry Keeler
  - Correspondence May 1851-December 1852 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous Osborn family Members
  - Correspondence and papers (Box 1)
- Dr. Harriette Osborn McCalmont Stone (b. 1867)
  (wife of Dr. W.A. Stone)
  - Biographical and miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (largely from parents) undated, 1878-1898, 30 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence 1912, 1917, 1920, 1926, 1928 (Box 2)
  - Writings (Box 2)
  - Invitations and Programs (Box 2)
  - Diary 1899-January 1901 (Box 2)
  - Clippings (Box 2)
- Visual Materials
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Woodcuts (Box 2)